<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Prayer | My Octopress Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://veromary.github.io/blog/categories/prayer/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://veromary.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-09-23T11:17:07+10:00</updated>
  <id>http://veromary.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Veronica Brandt]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[veronica@brandt.id.au]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[15th Sunday after Pentecost]]></title>
    <link href="http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/08/28/15th-sunday-after-pentecost/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-28T15:14:41+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/08/28/15th-sunday-after-pentecost</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/WidowAtNaim.jpg"><img src="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/WidowAtNaim-213x300.jpg" alt="WidowAtNaim" /></a>Rejoice with me!  for the book that was lost is found!</p>

<p>This Sunday&rsquo;s Gospel tells of Jesus raising the son of the widow of Naim.</p>

<blockquote><p>Et resedit, qui erat mortuus.</p></blockquote>

<p>And he who was dead sat up.</p>

<p>And here is the worksheet: <a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/15th-Sunday-after-Pentecost.pdf">15th Sunday after Pentecost</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[12th Sunday post Pentecost]]></title>
    <link href="http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/08/06/12th-sunday-post-pentecost/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-06T11:40:58+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/08/06/12th-sunday-post-pentecost</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/cyclopedia-goodsamaritan-sm.png"><img src="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/cyclopedia-goodsamaritan-sm-300x253.png" alt="cyclopedia-goodsamaritan-sm" /></a>And turning to his disciples, he said: Blessed are the eyes that see the things which you see.  For I say to you, that many prophets and kings have desired to see the things that you see, and have not seen them; and to hear the things that you hear, and have not heard them.  And behold a certain lawyer stood up, tempting him, and saying, Master, what must I do to possess eternal life?</p>

<p>But he said to him: What is written in the law? how readest thou?  He answering, said: Thou shalt love the Lord thy God with thy whole heart, and with thy whole soul, and with all thy strength, and with all thy mind: and thy neighbour as thyself.  And he said to him: Thou hast answered right: this do, and thou shalt live.  But he willing to justify himself, said to Jesus: And who is my neighbour?  And Jesus answering, said: A certain man went down from Jerusalem to Jericho, and fell among robbers, who also stripped him, and having wounded him went away, leaving him half dead.</p>

<p>And it chanced, that a certain priest went down the same way: and seeing him, passed by.  In like manner also a Levite, when he was near the place and saw him, passed by.  But a certain Samaritan being on his journey, came near him; and seeing him, was moved with compassion.  And going up to him, bound up his wounds, pouring in oil and wine: and setting him upon his own beast, brought him to an inn, and took care of him.  And the next day he took out two pence, and gave to the host, and said: Take care of him; and whatsoever thou shalt spend over and above, I, at my return, will repay thee.</p>

<p>Which of these three, in thy opinion, was neighbour to him that fell among the robbers?  But he said: He that shewed mercy to him. And Jesus said to him: Go, and do thou in like manner.</p>

<p>Vade, et fac similiter.</p>

<p><strong>Here is the Kids Mass Sheet: <a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/Pentecost12.odt">Pentecost12</a></strong></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[11th Sunday after Pentecost]]></title>
    <link href="http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/07/30/11th-sunday-after-pentecost/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-30T15:32:29+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/07/30/11th-sunday-after-pentecost</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/Blind-MChalmers-sm.jpg"><img src="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/Blind-MChalmers-sm-204x300.jpg" alt="Blind-MChalmers-sm" /></a>This colour illustration is from The Bible Picture Book by Muriel Chalmers.  I can&rsquo;t find the Rev. Hole book this afternoon.  Hopefully it will turn up soon!</p>

<p>At that time, Jesus going out of the coasts of Tyre, came by Sidon to the sea of Galilee, through the midst of the coasts of Decapolis. And they bring to Him one deaf and dumb, and they besought Him that He would lay His hand upon him. And taking him from the multitude apart, He put His fingers into his ears, and spitting, He touched his tongue; and looking up to heaven, He groaned and said to him: Ephphetha, which is, Be thou opened: and immediately his ears were opened, and the string of his tongue was loosed, and he spoke right. And He charged them that they should tell no man: but the more He charged them so much the more a great deal did they publish it; and so much the more did they wonder, saying: He hath done all things well; He hath made both the deaf to hear and the dumb to speak.</p>

<p><a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/Pente11Nadal.png"><img src="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/Pente11Nadal-185x300.png" alt="Pente11Nadal" /></a></p>

<blockquote><p>Bene ómnia fecit</p></blockquote>

<p>He hath done all things well</p>

<p>And here is the Kids Mass Sheet:
<a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/Pentecost11.pdf">Pentecost11.pdf</a></p>

<p>And for those who might be curious, here is how to write Ephpheta in Greek letters:
εφφαθα</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[10th sunday post pentecost]]></title>
    <link href="http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/07/25/10th-sunday-post-pentecost/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-25T07:12:09+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/07/25/10th-sunday-post-pentecost</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/PenteNadal10.png"><img src="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/PenteNadal10-183x300.png" alt="PenteNadal10" /></a>At that time, Jesus spoke this parable to some who trusted in themselves as just, and despised others. Two men went up into the temple to pray; the one a Pharisee, and the other a Publican. The Pharisee standing, prayed thus with himself: O God, I give Thee thanks that I am not as the rest of men, extortioners, unjust, adulterers; as also is this publican. I fast twice in the week; I give tithes of all that I possess. And the Publican standing afar off would not so much as lift up his eyes towards heaven, but struck his breast saying: O God, be merciful to me a sinner. I say to you, this man went down to his house justified rather than the other: because every one that exalteth himself shall be humbled, and he that humbleth himself shall be exalted.</p>

<p><a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/cyclopedia-phariseepub-sm.png"><img src="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/cyclopedia-phariseepub-sm-300x252.png" alt="cyclopedia-phariseepub-sm" /></a>And here is the kids Mass sheet: <a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/Pentecost10.pdf">Pentecost10</a></p>

<blockquote><p>Deus, propítius esto mihi peccatóri.</p></blockquote>

<p>O God, be merciful to me a sinner.</p>

<p>Have a good weekend!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Little hymn for the little hours of the little office]]></title>
    <link href="http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/07/19/little-hymn-for-the-little-hours-of-the-little-office/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-19T15:37:23+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/07/19/little-hymn-for-the-little-hours-of-the-little-office</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/immaculate-heart-of-mary.jpg"><img src="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/immaculate-heart-of-mary-242x300.jpg" alt="immaculate-heart-of-mary" /></a>Right now our family just does two hours, Prime and Compline.  I&rsquo;ve mentioned the <a href="http://brandt.id.au/music/te-lucis-ante-terminum/">hymn for Compline earlier</a>.  We did try singing Prime from the regular Divine Office, but found it a bit difficult.  Instead we settled on the Little Office version.  It&rsquo;s the same each day, with minor seasonal variations for Advent and Christmas.</p>

<p>The Divine Office has different hymns for each hour: Jam Lucis for Prime, Nunc Sancte Nobis for Terce, Rector Potens for Sext, Rerum Deus for None and Te Lucis for Compline.  Matins, Lauds and Vespers have different hymns for each day of the week and different feast days and seasons.  The Little Office of the Blessed Virgin Mary has much fewer hymns and most of them to the one tune.</p>

<p>This is the hymn for Prime, Terce, Sext, None and Compline:</p>

<p>Memento, rerum Conditor,
Nostri quod olim corporis,
Sacrata ab alvo Virginis
Nascendo formam sumpseris.</p>

<p>Maria, Mater gratiæ,
Dulcis parens clementiæ,
Tu nos ab hoste protege
Et mortis hora suscipe.</p>

<p>Jesu, tibi sit gloria,
Qui natus es de Virgine,
Cum Patre, et almo Spiritu,
In sempiterna sæcula. Amen.</p>

<p>Remember, O Creator Lord,
that in the Virgin&rsquo;s sacred womb
Thou wast conceived, and of her flesh
didst our mortality assume.</p>

<p>Mother of grace, O Mary blest,
to thee, sweet fount of love, we fly;
shield us through life, and take us hence
to thy dear bosom when we die.</p>

<p>O Jesu! born of Mary bright!
Immortal glory be to Thee;
praise to the Father infinite,
and Holy Ghost eternally. Amen.</p>

<p>Matins and Lauds have slightly longer hymns, but same tune.</p>

<p>Some collections of chant have a shorter version, just taking the last two verses of Memento, as sung in this clip from youtube:</p>

<p>So, for singing along, here is the sheet music: <a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/MementoRerum.pdf">MementoRerum</a>
You might remember last weeks diversion into the differences in chant hymns introduced by Pope Urban VIII.  Here is the earlier, medieval wording: <a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/MementoSalutis.pdf">MementoSalutis</a>.  Which is also the same wording that William Byrd used in <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=722E-rjD5Nw">a beautiful polyphonic arrangement</a>.</p>

<p>Those pages are from a book I was working on which is up at <a href="http://github.com/veromary/littleOffice">github/veromary/littleOffice</a>.  A booklet with Prime and Compline from the little office, plus the text of the Gospel Canticles, Benedictus and Magnificat.  For a recording of our family singing compline from these books see <a href="http://repleatur.net/2012/10/10/compline-from-the-little-office-of-bvm/">Compline from the Little Office</a> over at my choir blog.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
