<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[My Octopress Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://veromary.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://veromary.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-09-23T11:17:07+10:00</updated>
  <id>http://veromary.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Veronica Brandt]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[veronica@brandt.id.au]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[All quiet]]></title>
    <link href="http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/09/21/all-quiet/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-21T17:45:21+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/09/21/all-quiet</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Begging your pardon for not posting regularly.</p>

<p>I have half a mind to go back to a static website, maybe along the lines of <a href="http://veromary.github.io">veromary.github.io</a>.</p>

<p>Peter is selling portraits on <a href="http://www.ebay.com.au/sch/swissbrandt-au/m.html">ebay</a> and <a href="http://avalonprand.etsy.com">etsy</a>.</p>

<p>Boys have had a go at <a href="http://diy.org">DIY.org</a>.  You can see their work <a href="https://diy.org/windpower">here</a> and <a href="https://diy.org/mischiefloki">here</a> and <a href="https://diy.org/wolfhunter">here</a> and <a href="https://diy.org/misterswoop">here</a>.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m still blogging for <a href="http://ccwatershed.org">ccwatershed.org</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[15th Sunday after Pentecost]]></title>
    <link href="http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/08/28/15th-sunday-after-pentecost/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-28T15:14:41+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/08/28/15th-sunday-after-pentecost</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/WidowAtNaim.jpg"><img src="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/WidowAtNaim-213x300.jpg" alt="WidowAtNaim" /></a>Rejoice with me!  for the book that was lost is found!</p>

<p>This Sunday&rsquo;s Gospel tells of Jesus raising the son of the widow of Naim.</p>

<blockquote><p>Et resedit, qui erat mortuus.</p></blockquote>

<p>And he who was dead sat up.</p>

<p>And here is the worksheet: <a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/15th-Sunday-after-Pentecost.pdf">15th Sunday after Pentecost</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[First-post]]></title>
    <link href="http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/08/24/first-post/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-24T15:15:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/08/24/first-post</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Here goes nothing.</p>

<p>Hello, welcome to the latest in a long line of webpages set up by itinerant troublemaker VB.  Much of this new website is very new to me.  It might just help me get my act together and finish a few projects!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[12th Sunday post Pentecost]]></title>
    <link href="http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/08/06/12th-sunday-post-pentecost/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-06T11:40:58+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/08/06/12th-sunday-post-pentecost</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/cyclopedia-goodsamaritan-sm.png"><img src="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/cyclopedia-goodsamaritan-sm-300x253.png" alt="cyclopedia-goodsamaritan-sm" /></a>And turning to his disciples, he said: Blessed are the eyes that see the things which you see.  For I say to you, that many prophets and kings have desired to see the things that you see, and have not seen them; and to hear the things that you hear, and have not heard them.  And behold a certain lawyer stood up, tempting him, and saying, Master, what must I do to possess eternal life?</p>

<p>But he said to him: What is written in the law? how readest thou?  He answering, said: Thou shalt love the Lord thy God with thy whole heart, and with thy whole soul, and with all thy strength, and with all thy mind: and thy neighbour as thyself.  And he said to him: Thou hast answered right: this do, and thou shalt live.  But he willing to justify himself, said to Jesus: And who is my neighbour?  And Jesus answering, said: A certain man went down from Jerusalem to Jericho, and fell among robbers, who also stripped him, and having wounded him went away, leaving him half dead.</p>

<p>And it chanced, that a certain priest went down the same way: and seeing him, passed by.  In like manner also a Levite, when he was near the place and saw him, passed by.  But a certain Samaritan being on his journey, came near him; and seeing him, was moved with compassion.  And going up to him, bound up his wounds, pouring in oil and wine: and setting him upon his own beast, brought him to an inn, and took care of him.  And the next day he took out two pence, and gave to the host, and said: Take care of him; and whatsoever thou shalt spend over and above, I, at my return, will repay thee.</p>

<p>Which of these three, in thy opinion, was neighbour to him that fell among the robbers?  But he said: He that shewed mercy to him. And Jesus said to him: Go, and do thou in like manner.</p>

<p>Vade, et fac similiter.</p>

<p><strong>Here is the Kids Mass Sheet: <a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/Pentecost12.odt">Pentecost12</a></strong></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[11th Sunday after Pentecost]]></title>
    <link href="http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/07/30/11th-sunday-after-pentecost/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-30T15:32:29+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/07/30/11th-sunday-after-pentecost</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/Blind-MChalmers-sm.jpg"><img src="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/Blind-MChalmers-sm-204x300.jpg" alt="Blind-MChalmers-sm" /></a>This colour illustration is from The Bible Picture Book by Muriel Chalmers.  I can&rsquo;t find the Rev. Hole book this afternoon.  Hopefully it will turn up soon!</p>

<p>At that time, Jesus going out of the coasts of Tyre, came by Sidon to the sea of Galilee, through the midst of the coasts of Decapolis. And they bring to Him one deaf and dumb, and they besought Him that He would lay His hand upon him. And taking him from the multitude apart, He put His fingers into his ears, and spitting, He touched his tongue; and looking up to heaven, He groaned and said to him: Ephphetha, which is, Be thou opened: and immediately his ears were opened, and the string of his tongue was loosed, and he spoke right. And He charged them that they should tell no man: but the more He charged them so much the more a great deal did they publish it; and so much the more did they wonder, saying: He hath done all things well; He hath made both the deaf to hear and the dumb to speak.</p>

<p><a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/Pente11Nadal.png"><img src="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/Pente11Nadal-185x300.png" alt="Pente11Nadal" /></a></p>

<blockquote><p>Bene ómnia fecit</p></blockquote>

<p>He hath done all things well</p>

<p>And here is the Kids Mass Sheet:
<a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/Pentecost11.pdf">Pentecost11.pdf</a></p>

<p>And for those who might be curious, here is how to write Ephpheta in Greek letters:
εφφαθα</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Angelus]]></title>
    <link href="http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/07/26/angelus/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-26T13:36:55+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/07/26/angelus</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/martini-annunciazione.jpg"><img src="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/martini-annunciazione-300x189.jpg" alt="martini-annunciazione" /></a>Traditionally said every day at 6am, 12noon and 6pm, commemorating the Annunciation of Our Lord by the Angel Gabriel to Mary.  We had this in my primary school &ndash; a year six student would read it out over the public address system everyday at noon.  In the Philippines it would be said over the radio.  In medieval times the church bell would remind people for miles around to take a moment to pray.</p>

<p>In Easter time it is replaced by Regina Caeli (O Queen of Heaven rejoice!) which has music, but the rest of the year we usually just say it.</p>

<p>℣ Angelus Domini nuntiavit Mariae;
℟ Et concepit de Spiritu Sancto.
Ave Maria, gratia plena, Dominus tecum. Benedicta tu in mulieribus, et benedictus fructus ventris tui, Iesus. Sancta Maria, Mater Dei, ora pro nobis peccatoribus, nunc, et in hora mortis nostrae. Amen.
℣ Ecce ancilla Domini.
℟  Fiat mihi secundum verbum tuum.
Ave Maria, gratia plena,&hellip;
℣ Et Verbum caro factum est.
℟  Et habitavit in nobis.
Ave Maria, gratia plena,&hellip;
℣ Ora pro nobis, sancta Dei Genetrix.
℟  Ut digni efficiamur promissionibus Christi.
Oremus:
Gratiam tuam, quaesumus, Domine, mentibus nostris infunde; ut qui, Angelo nuntiante, Christi Filii tui incarnationem cognovimus, per passionem eius et crucem, ad resurrectionis gloriam perducamur. Per eundem Christum Dominum nostrum.
℟  Amen.</p>

<p>℣ The angel of the Lord declared unto Mary;
℟ And she conceived of the Holy Spirit.Hail Mary, full of grace, the Lord is with thee. Blessed art thou amongst women and blessed is the fruit of thy womb, Jesus. Holy Mary, Mother of God, pray for us sinners, now, and in the hour of our death. Amen.
℣ Behold the handmaid of the Lord:
℟  Be it done unto me according to Thy word.
Hail Mary, full of grace, &hellip;
℣ And the Word was made flesh:
℟  And dwelt among us.
Hail Mary, full of grace, &hellip;
℣ Pray for us, O Holy Mother of God.
℟  That we may be made worthy of the promises of Christ.
Let us pray:
Pour forth, we beseech Thee, O Lord, Thy grace into our hearts, that we, to whom the incarnation of Christ, Thy Son, was made known by the message of an angel, may by His passion and cross be brought to the glory of His resurrection, through the same Christ our Lord.
℟  Amen.</p>

<p>There are settings to sing the Angelus.  Here is one by Dom Charpentier OSB.  He uses a common antiphon tune in mode 4.  Sheet music <a href="http://lalemantpolyphonic.org/05_temp_Psalm_tone_samples/angelus_sung_PDF.pdf">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Soul of my Saviour]]></title>
    <link href="http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/07/25/soul-of-my-saviour/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-25T21:51:10+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/07/25/soul-of-my-saviour</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/St-Peter-Julian-Eymard.jpg"><img src="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/St-Peter-Julian-Eymard-208x300.jpg" alt="St Peter Julian Eymard" /></a>This is my favourite hymn for a thanksgiving after communion.</p>

<blockquote><p>Soul of my Savior sanctify my breast,
Body of Christ, be thou my saving guest,
Blood of my Savior, bathe me in thy tide,
wash me with waters gushing from thy side.</p></blockquote>

<p>Strength and protection may thy passion be,
O blessèd Jesus, hear and answer me;
deep in thy wounds, Lord, hide and shelter me,
so shall I never, never part from thee.</p>

<p>Guard and defend me from the foe malign,
in death&rsquo;s dread moments make me only thine;
call me and bid me come to thee on high
where I may praise thee with thy saints for ay.</p>

<p>Sheet music available at <a href="http://musicasacra.com/music/english-hymns-in-the-commons/">English hymns in the commons</a> thanks to the Church Music Association of America</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[10th sunday post pentecost]]></title>
    <link href="http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/07/25/10th-sunday-post-pentecost/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-25T07:12:09+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/07/25/10th-sunday-post-pentecost</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/PenteNadal10.png"><img src="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/PenteNadal10-183x300.png" alt="PenteNadal10" /></a>At that time, Jesus spoke this parable to some who trusted in themselves as just, and despised others. Two men went up into the temple to pray; the one a Pharisee, and the other a Publican. The Pharisee standing, prayed thus with himself: O God, I give Thee thanks that I am not as the rest of men, extortioners, unjust, adulterers; as also is this publican. I fast twice in the week; I give tithes of all that I possess. And the Publican standing afar off would not so much as lift up his eyes towards heaven, but struck his breast saying: O God, be merciful to me a sinner. I say to you, this man went down to his house justified rather than the other: because every one that exalteth himself shall be humbled, and he that humbleth himself shall be exalted.</p>

<p><a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/cyclopedia-phariseepub-sm.png"><img src="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/cyclopedia-phariseepub-sm-300x252.png" alt="cyclopedia-phariseepub-sm" /></a>And here is the kids Mass sheet: <a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/Pentecost10.pdf">Pentecost10</a></p>

<blockquote><p>Deus, propítius esto mihi peccatóri.</p></blockquote>

<p>O God, be merciful to me a sinner.</p>

<p>Have a good weekend!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Holy God, we praise Thy Name!]]></title>
    <link href="http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/07/19/holy-god-we-praise-thy-name/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-19T19:54:22+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/07/19/holy-god-we-praise-thy-name</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/communion-of-saints.jpg" alt="communion-of-saints" />This is a well known hymn.  It is based on the Ambrosian hymn <em>Te Deum</em>, a hymn of thanksgiving &ndash; <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MhUUvCxxsuY">here is a recording of Giovani Vianini jamming on the organ</a>.  But I&rsquo;m wandering &ndash; this is the vernacular hymn of the week post.</p>

<p>The <em>Te Deum</em> was anonymously paraphrased into German but later attributed to Ignaz Franz, then translated into English by Clarence Walworth from New York.  I&rsquo;ve heard that it is the standard post-benediction hymn in the United States.</p>

<p>Liturgically, there are times when the Te Deum is not sung, in times with a more penitential flavour like Lent, so Holy God is not quite a &ldquo;hymn for all seasons&rdquo;.  But pretty close.</p>

<blockquote><p>Holy God, we praise Thy Name;
Lord of all, we bow before Thee!
All on earth Thy scepter claim,
All in Heaven above adore Thee;
Infinite Thy vast domain,
Everlasting is Thy reign.</p></blockquote>

<p>Hark! the loud celestial hymn
Angel choirs above are raising,
Cherubim and seraphim,
In unceasing chorus praising;
Fill the heavens with sweet accord:
Holy, holy, holy, Lord.</p>

<p>Lo! the apostolic train
Join the sacred Name to hallow;
Prophets swell the loud refrain,
And the white robed martyrs follow;
And from morn to set of sun,
Through the Church the song goes on.</p>

<p>Holy Father, Holy Son,
Holy Spirit, Three we name Thee;
While in essence only One,
Undivided God we claim Thee;
And adoring bend the knee,
While we own the mystery.</p>

<p>Thou art King of glory, Christ:
Son of God, yet born of Mary;
For us sinners sacrificed,
And to death a tributary:
First to break the bars of death,
Thou has opened Heaven to faith.</p>

<p>From Thy high celestial home,
Judge of all, again returning,
We believe that Thou shalt come
In the dreaded doomsday morning;
When Thy voice shall shake the earth,
And the startled dead come forth.</p>

<p><em>Therefore do we pray Thee, Lord:
Help Thy servants whom, redeeming
By Thy precious blood out-poured,
Thou hast saved from Satan’s scheming.
Give to them eternal rest
In the glory of the blest.</em></p>

<p>Spare Thy people, Lord, we pray,
By a thousand snares surrounded:
Keep us without sin today,
Never let us be confounded.
Lo, I put my trust in Thee;
Never, Lord, abandon me.</p>

<p>*This verse a later addition by Hugh T. Henry.</p>

<p>Here is the sheet music from the Vatican II hymnbook by Corpus Christi Watershed <a href="http://www.ccwatershed.org/pdfs/217-holy-god-we-praise-thy-name-grosser-gott-hh3/download/">Holy God/Grosser Gott</a>.</p>

<p>Here is my easy play version <a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/holyGod.pdf">holyGod</a> (with lilypond source: <a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/holyGod.ly">holyGod</a>)</p>

<p>And the obligatory recording, in case you haven&rsquo;t heard it already:</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Little hymn for the little hours of the little office]]></title>
    <link href="http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/07/19/little-hymn-for-the-little-hours-of-the-little-office/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-19T15:37:23+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/07/19/little-hymn-for-the-little-hours-of-the-little-office</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/immaculate-heart-of-mary.jpg"><img src="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/immaculate-heart-of-mary-242x300.jpg" alt="immaculate-heart-of-mary" /></a>Right now our family just does two hours, Prime and Compline.  I&rsquo;ve mentioned the <a href="http://brandt.id.au/music/te-lucis-ante-terminum/">hymn for Compline earlier</a>.  We did try singing Prime from the regular Divine Office, but found it a bit difficult.  Instead we settled on the Little Office version.  It&rsquo;s the same each day, with minor seasonal variations for Advent and Christmas.</p>

<p>The Divine Office has different hymns for each hour: Jam Lucis for Prime, Nunc Sancte Nobis for Terce, Rector Potens for Sext, Rerum Deus for None and Te Lucis for Compline.  Matins, Lauds and Vespers have different hymns for each day of the week and different feast days and seasons.  The Little Office of the Blessed Virgin Mary has much fewer hymns and most of them to the one tune.</p>

<p>This is the hymn for Prime, Terce, Sext, None and Compline:</p>

<p>Memento, rerum Conditor,
Nostri quod olim corporis,
Sacrata ab alvo Virginis
Nascendo formam sumpseris.</p>

<p>Maria, Mater gratiæ,
Dulcis parens clementiæ,
Tu nos ab hoste protege
Et mortis hora suscipe.</p>

<p>Jesu, tibi sit gloria,
Qui natus es de Virgine,
Cum Patre, et almo Spiritu,
In sempiterna sæcula. Amen.</p>

<p>Remember, O Creator Lord,
that in the Virgin&rsquo;s sacred womb
Thou wast conceived, and of her flesh
didst our mortality assume.</p>

<p>Mother of grace, O Mary blest,
to thee, sweet fount of love, we fly;
shield us through life, and take us hence
to thy dear bosom when we die.</p>

<p>O Jesu! born of Mary bright!
Immortal glory be to Thee;
praise to the Father infinite,
and Holy Ghost eternally. Amen.</p>

<p>Matins and Lauds have slightly longer hymns, but same tune.</p>

<p>Some collections of chant have a shorter version, just taking the last two verses of Memento, as sung in this clip from youtube:</p>

<p>So, for singing along, here is the sheet music: <a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/MementoRerum.pdf">MementoRerum</a>
You might remember last weeks diversion into the differences in chant hymns introduced by Pope Urban VIII.  Here is the earlier, medieval wording: <a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/MementoSalutis.pdf">MementoSalutis</a>.  Which is also the same wording that William Byrd used in <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=722E-rjD5Nw">a beautiful polyphonic arrangement</a>.</p>

<p>Those pages are from a book I was working on which is up at <a href="http://github.com/veromary/littleOffice">github/veromary/littleOffice</a>.  A booklet with Prime and Compline from the little office, plus the text of the Gospel Canticles, Benedictus and Magnificat.  For a recording of our family singing compline from these books see <a href="http://repleatur.net/2012/10/10/compline-from-the-little-office-of-bvm/">Compline from the Little Office</a> over at my choir blog.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[9th Sunday after Pentecost]]></title>
    <link href="http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/07/17/9th-sunday-after-pentecost/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-17T16:06:19+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/07/17/9th-sunday-after-pentecost</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/WHole020.jpg"><img src="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/WHole020-216x300.jpg" alt="WHole020" /></a>When I went to get this week&rsquo;s illustration from William Hole&rsquo;s <em>The Life of Jesus of Nazareth</em>.  The reading for this week corresponds with the picture of Jesus teaching in the temple that I picked <a href="http://brandt.id.au/prayer/8th-sunday-after-pentecost/">last week!</a>  But not to worry.  This weeks picture is near the beginning of the Public Ministry according to John&rsquo;s Gospel.  Today&rsquo;s reading is from Luke again:</p>

<p>At that time, when Jesus drew near to Jerusalem, seeing the city, He wept over it saying: If thou also hadst known, and that in this day, the things that are to thy peace: but now they are hidden from thy eyes. For the days shall come upon thee, and thy enemies shall cast a trench about thee, and compass thee round, and straiten thee on every side; and beat thee flat to the ground, and thy children who are in thee; and they shall not leave in thee a stone upon a stone, because thou hast not known the time of thy visitation. And entering into the temple, He began to cast out them that sold therein, and them that bought, saying to them: It is written, My house is the house of prayer, but you have made it a den of thieves. And He was teaching daily in the temple.</p>

<p><a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/Nadal088.png"><img src="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/Nadal088-186x300.png" alt="Nadal088" /></a>Here is the printable page: <a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/Pentecost09.pdf">Pentecost09.pdf</a></p>

<blockquote><p>Quia domus mea domus oratiónis est.</p></blockquote>

<p>My house is the house of prayer.</p>

<p>Nadal&rsquo;s picture is great, as usual.  I like the line for label B: Christi splendor e vultu &amp; maiestas quae terret omnes.  Something like &ldquo;the splendor of Christ&rsquo;s face/countenance strikes terror into all&rdquo;.  Yes, I need to study more.</p>

<p>Yes, the astute reader will notice this is for Feria III post Dominica I in Quadragesimae (Tuesday after the first Sunday of Lent).  Same picture so Felix Just only put up the one.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[LMS for a homeschool]]></title>
    <link href="http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/07/17/lms-for-a-homeschool/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-17T11:58:34+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/07/17/lms-for-a-homeschool</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/jumblelms.png"><img src="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/jumblelms.png" alt="jumblelms" /></a>My project for the winter holidays was to make an online course to go through the multiplication tables with my four sons, ages 6 &ndash; 11.  It was meant to be an pleasant diversion from regular homeschooling, but turned into an epic learning experience!</p>

<p>There are many options out there.  My little collage of logos there you&rsquo;ll see some open sources LMSs: <a href="http://moodle.org">Moodle</a>, <a href="http://chamilo.org">Chamilo</a> and <a href="http://claroline.net">Claroline</a>; a couple of hosted services: <a href="https://www.udemy.com/">udemy</a> and <a href="http://www.talentlms.com/">TalentLMS</a> and, lastly, some helpful tools <a href="http://wordpress.org">WordPress</a>, <a href="http://hotpot.uvic.ca/">Hot Potatoes</a> and <a href="http://www.randelshofer.ch/tinylms/">TinyLMS</a>.  There are more out there.  Another open source LMS I installed was <a href="http://www.efrontlearning.net/">efront learning</a> &ndash; which may be related to TalentLMS (see above).</p>

<h2>Self-hosted LMS</h2>

<p>At first (after my last look at the idea some years ago), I was settled on <a href="http://chamilo.org">Chamilo</a>, a very handsome Learning Management System (LMS).  It comes in two flavours right now, 1.9.6 and <a href="http://lcms.chamilo.org/">LCMS Connect</a>.  They are both great &ndash; 1.9.6 looks better for the K-6 age range, but Connect is a bit more sophisticated.</p>

<p>It was all going well until I had a mysterious problem where one computer would refuse to show any webpages from my webhosting.  Other websites would load fine.  My home internet access is not the greatest, so slow patches are par for the course, but sometimes it would be just my webpages that were running slowly.</p>

<p>I learned about Shared Hosting vs VPS.  Also that having several students logged in at the same time on your average LMS requires hefty web hosting &ndash; not your Economy class shared hosting.  Most of the information on this phenomenon refers to the Great <a href="http://moodle.org">Moodle</a> of Western Australia, but applies to Chamilo and other LMSs too. It might work if you installed the LMS on your own network at home, but I have not networked my home computers.  Some estimate the server would need 2Gb RAM to be on the safe side.</p>

<p>So, now I reluctantly turn my gaze from the beautiful, shiny, self-hosted, open source LMSs.  There seem to be two options: a) make do with webpages with simple quiz things or b) sell out and use a commercial service.</p>

<h2>Webpages with quizzes</h2>

<p>This is a Wordpress blog, so it makes sense to explore what I already have up and running.  There are LMS plugins, like the free <a href="http://namaste-lms.org/">Namaste!</a> or many, many, many paid services.  Namaste! has a catch, that it works with an exam plugin, which has a basic free version and a range of paid premium versions.</p>

<p>I can do my own &ldquo;course&rdquo; by making webpages, each ending with a quiz to be passed to reveal the address of the next page plus a form to submit the results to my email.  This is fiddly, but gets the consistent looks of this blog, plus it hopefully won&rsquo;t exceed the shared hosting limits like Chamilo did.  It&rsquo;s fiddly to set up, but it&rsquo;s cheap.</p>

<p>There are some tools for making this easier.  <a href="http://www.randelshofer.ch/tinylms/">TinyLMS</a> takes a SCORM package and formats it for web and/or printing.  The resulting webpages can be put online, on CD, or even zipped up and emailed to students.  All you need is a SCORM editor, like <a href="http://exelearning.org/">eXe learning</a> from New Zealand and <a href="http://www.reload.ac.uk/">RELOAD</a> from the UK which both seem to be very quiet lately.  The RELOAD website displays a notice that they are undergoing an overhaul, dated July 2008.  There is a new one called <a href="http://sourceforge.net/p/exe-nextgen/">EXE Next Gen</a> from Afghanistan which looks Great.  They seem to have fixed up the NZ eXe and enhanced it.  It exports to several formats including one for mobiles.  Unfortunately my debian box doesn&rsquo;t seem to like the ubuntu packages, but something to bear in mind.  (<strong>Update:</strong> there is a current, working version of eXe at <a href="http://exelearning.net/?lang=en">exelearning.net</a> based in Spain.)</p>

<p>And I should mention <a href="http://hotpot.uvic.ca">Hot Potatoes</a> a Windows program that works on Linux under wine.  It makes javascript quizzes that you can export as webpages and upload as they are or embed into blogs like this.  Their philosophy is not so much assessment, but doing exercises to help you learn.</p>

<h2>Going commercial</h2>

<p>There are many companies only too willing to set up your LMS for a fee.  Some are particularly interesting to homeschoolers since they have a free version for a limited number of students &ndash; which, depending on the size of your family, might suit you right down to the ground.  On the other hand, if you want to share your courses with other families then someone has to start paying.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve started a site at <a href="http://talentlms.com">talentLMS</a> which is reminiscent of the free <a href="http://efrontlearning.org">efront learning</a> and they both come from Greece.  It is very slick.  For the time being <a href="http://brandt.talentlms.com/shared/start/key:GBKMFPJU">this is my multiplication course</a>.  We&rsquo;ll see how it goes.</p>

<h2>In conclusion</h2>

<p>I would have liked to show off my Chamilo install here, but it would bring down the rest of my webpages.  I have learnt a bit about the limits of what is possible on the internet.  Maybe, as time goes by, the price of strong hosting will come down, but then again, there will always be fancier software available to tax the servers.</p>

<p>If you want to pay $30 per month for something, consider <a href="http://www.churchinneed.org/">Aid to the Church in Need</a>, <a href="http://fli.org">Family Life International</a> or <a href="http://fatima.org.au">Australia Needs Fatima</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Veni Creator]]></title>
    <link href="http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/07/12/veni-creator/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-12T22:27:07+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/07/12/veni-creator</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Gian_Lorenzo_Bernini_-_Dove_of_the_Holy_Spirit.JPG"><img src="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/Gian_Lorenzo_Bernini_-_Dove_of_the_Holy_Spirit.jpg" alt="Gian_Lorenzo_Bernini_-_Dove_of_the_Holy_Spirit" /></a>Good old hymn to the Holy Ghost.  Great for just about every special occasion &ndash; confirmations, ordinations, baptisms, weddings, any time you pray for a blessing!</p>

<p>Here is my one page special sheet music: <a href="http://repleatur.net/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/venicreator.pdf">venicreator.pdf</a>.</p>

<p>And here are the words:</p>

<blockquote><ol>
<li>Veni, creator Spiritus
mentes tuorum visita,
imple superna gratia,
quae tu creasti pectora.</li>
</ol>
</blockquote>

<ol>
<li><p>Qui diceris Paraclitus,
altissimi donum Dei,
fons vivus, ignis, caritas
et spiritalis unctio.</p></li>
<li><p>Tu septiformis munere,
digitus paternae dexterae
tu rite promissum Patris
sermone ditans guttura.</p></li>
<li><p>Accende lumen sensibus,
infunde amorem cordibus,
infirma nostri corporis,
virtute firmans perpeti.</p></li>
<li><p>Hostem repellas longius
pacemque dones protinus;
ductore sic te praevio
vitemus omne noxium.</p></li>
<li><p>Per te sciamus da Patrem
noscamus atque Filium,
te utriusque Spiritum
credamus omni tempore.</p></li>
<li><p>Deo Patri sit gloria,
et Filio qui a mortuis
Surrexit, ac Paraclito,
in saeculorum saecula.
Amen.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>There are two popular translations that I know of.  <a href="http://www.hymntime.com/tch/htm/c/o/m/e/comehogo.htm">Come Holy Ghost, Creator Come</a> &ndash; in a nice steady 86.86 rhythm and <a href="http://www.smallchurchmusic.com/index.php?RSongID=2284">Come Holy Ghost, Creator Blest</a> in 88.88 like the original Latin.  They are both really beautiful.  Both worth planting in your memory.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.cpdl.org/wiki/index.php/Veni_Creator_Spiritus">Choral Public Domain Library</a> has more information, including a link to the <a href="http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/15341a.htm">Catholic Encyclopedia article</a> which gives the first part of <a href="http://www.hymntime.com/tch/htm/c/r/e/creators.htm">John Dryden&rsquo;s translation</a>.</p>

<p>Lastly, there is <a href="http://gregobase.selapa.net/chant.php?id=3241">another version</a> of the Latin <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cDhYGdK0KQg">sung by Giovanni Vianini&rsquo;s choirs</a>.  This is the one found in the Monastic Antiphonale, used by Benedictine monasteries.  The story of why there are two versions of so many hymns can be read: <a href="http://www.ewtn.com/library/liturgy/revishym.txt">URBAN VIII AND THE REVISION OF THE LATIN HYMNAL by Vincent A. Lenti</a>.  Basically, we had all these hymns for a thousand years or so, then in the 1500s, the humanist Pope Urban VIII thought &ldquo;that the old hymns were rather tasteless and inelegant and could be improved with a reworking of the Latin texts&rdquo;.  The Benedictines and other groups (including the Vatican) got permission to stick with the old hymns, so that&rsquo;s why they&rsquo;re in the Monastic books.  The rest of the Roman Rite got the humanist &ldquo;improved&rdquo; versions.  One of the wonderful changes with the whole recent overhaul of the liturgy was undoing Pope Urban VIII&rsquo;s changes and going back to the original hymns.  Unfortunately, the Extraordinary Form uses 1962 books, which still have the &ldquo;improved&rdquo; humanist versions.  So that&rsquo;s what I&rsquo;ve given here.</p>

<blockquote><p>&ldquo;Ambrose and Prudentius took something classical and made it Christian; the revisers and their imitators took something Christian and tried to make it classical. The result may be pedantry, and sometimes perhaps poetry; but it is not piety.&rdquo; &mdash; Rev. Joseph Connelly in <em>Hymns of the Roman Liturgy</em>, The Newmann Press, West minster, Maryland, 1957.</p></blockquote>

<p>God has it all fixed up in heaven.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Firmly I Believe]]></title>
    <link href="http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/07/12/firmly-i-believe/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-12T21:31:01+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/07/12/firmly-i-believe</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/CatechisminPcs56.png"><img src="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/CatechisminPcs56-212x300.png" alt="CatechisminPcs56" /></a>The words for this hymn are found in Cardinal Newman&rsquo;s poem the <a href="http://www.newmanreader.org/works/verses/gerontius.html">Dream of Gerontius</a>. It is the prayer of a soul preparing for death. Later in the poem the angels sing another of Cardinal Newman&rsquo;s famous hymns, Praise to the Holiest. It is a fantastic read.</p>

<p>It also gives something like a chorus to this hymn:</p>

<blockquote><p>Sanctus fortis, Sanctus Deus,
De profundis oro te,
Miserere, Judex meus,
Parce mihi, Domine.</p></blockquote>

<p>This chorus is given first and last and in the middle. A rough translation would be Holy Mighty One, Holy God, out of the depths I cry to There. Have Mercy, my Judge, spare me, Lord.</p>

<p>Edward Elgar made the poem into an oratorio, which is why most places use his tune, Drakes Broughton. It can be a majestic tune, but can be prone to plodding or even dragging.</p>

<p>I have enjoyed singing Firmly I Believe to the tune some call Omni Die, which sounds like a reference to the popular Marian hymn, Daily, daily sing to Mary.  Here&rsquo;s my easy organ music:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Elgar&rsquo;s tune: <a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/elgarFirmly.pdf">elgarFirmly.pdf</a><a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/elgarFirmly.ly">(lilypond source elgarFirmly.ly)</a> &ndash; youtube clip <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=C6LzyHiYrSM">here</a></p></li>
<li><p>More lively tune: <a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/FirmlyChords.pdf">FirmlyChords.pdf</a> (lilypond source <a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/FirmlyChords.ly">FirmlyChords.ly</a>) &ndash; hear the tune played better <a href="http://www.smallchurchmusic.com/index.php?RSongID=916">here</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.smallchurchmusic.com/index.php?RSongID=963">Small Church Music</a> has another tune called Sharon.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>However you sing it, call to mind the profession of faith of a soul on the brink of eternity.</p>

<blockquote><p>Firmly I believe and truly
God is Three, and God is One;
And I next acknowledge duly
Manhood taken by the Son.</p></blockquote>

<p>And I trust and hope most fully
In that manhood crucified;
And each thought and deed unruly
Do to death, as He has died.</p>

<p>Simply to His grace and wholly
Light and life and strength belong,
And I love supremely, solely,
Him the holy, Him the strong.</p>

<p>And I hold in veneration,
For the love of Him alone,
Holy Church as His creation,
And her teachings are His own.</p>

<p>And I take with joy whatever
Now besets me, pain or fear,
And with a strong will I sever
All the ties which bind me here.</p>

<p>Adoration aye be given,
With and through the angelic host,
To the God of earth and Heaven,
Father, Son and Holy Ghost.</p>

<p>That second last verse is often left out &ndash; it&rsquo;s more specific to the departing soul.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[8th Sunday after Pentecost]]></title>
    <link href="http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/07/11/8th-sunday-after-pentecost/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-11T14:34:56+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/07/11/8th-sunday-after-pentecost</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>[caption id=&ldquo;attachment_1153&rdquo; align=&ldquo;alignleft&rdquo; width=&ldquo;211&rdquo;]<a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/WHole053sm.jpg"><img src="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/WHole053sm-211x300.jpg" alt="plate 53 Luke 19" /></a> plate 53<br/>
Luke 19[/caption]This Sunday&rsquo;s reading is a tricky one.  Is Our Lord encouraging embezzlement?</p>

<p>I can&rsquo;t find a particular colour page.  This parable fits between the Good Samaritan and No Man Can Serve Two Masters.  The latter brings in some flack from the Pharisees, so I figured this picture will do, though I don&rsquo;t think he was actually teaching in the temple this time.</p>

<p>Here is the printable colouring page: <a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/Pentecost08.pdf">Pentecost08</a> &ndash; using Fr Nadal&rsquo;s work again.</p>

<blockquote><p>recípiant vos in ætérna tabernácula.</p></blockquote>

<p>they may receive you into everlasting dwellings.</p>

<p><a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/Pente08Nadal.png"><img src="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/Pente08Nadal-195x300.png" alt="Pente08Nadal" /></a>At that time, Jesus spoke to His disciples this parable: There was a certain rich man who had a steward; and the same was accused unto him that he had wasted his goods; and he called him, and said to him: How is it that I hear this of thee? Give an account of thy stewardship, for now thou canst be steward no longer. And the steward said within himself: What shall I do, because my lord taketh away from me the stewardship? To dig, I am not able: to beg, I am ashamed. I know what I will do, that when I shall be put out of the stewardship, they may receive me into their houses. Therefore calling together every one of his lord’s debtors, he said to the first: How much dost thou owe my lord? But he said: A hundred barrels of oil. And he said to him: Take thy bill, and sit down quickly, and write fifty. Then he said to another: And how much dost thou owe? Who said: A hundred quarters of wheat. He said to him: Take thy bill, and write eighty. And the lord commended the unjust steward, for as much as he had done wisely: for the children of this world are wiser in their generation than the children of light. And I say to you: Make unto you friends of the mammon of iniquity, that when you shall fail, they may receive you into everlasting dwellings.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[O purest of creatures]]></title>
    <link href="http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/07/05/o-purest-of-creatures/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-05T10:19:27+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/07/05/o-purest-of-creatures</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/immaculate-heart-of-mary.jpg" alt="immaculate-heart-of-mary" />Here&rsquo;s a hymn, the source of much consternation in the organ loft.  Many people sing it to the tune of the Lourdes Hymn, but all hymnbooks set it to the German tune from the Paderborn Gesangbuch.  Because hymnbook writers prefer the proper tune, but lazy pew potatoes go for the easy one.</p>

<p>Note, there are no &ldquo;Ave&#8221;s in this one.  That&rsquo;s a Lourdes Hymn thing.  Just a straight hymn to Our Lady.  Written by the oratorian priest, Fr Frederick Faber.  Famous for veering towards the sentimental side with his hymn writing.  I&rsquo;m sure he would have worn a surplice with a good 5 inches of lace at least.</p>

<blockquote><p>O purest of creatures! sweet Mother, sweet Maid;
The one spotless womb wherein Jesus was laid.
Dark night hath come down on us, Mother, and we
Look out for thy shining, sweet Star of the Sea.</p></blockquote>

<p>2 Deep night hath come down on this rough-spoken world.
And the banners of darkness are boldly unfurled;
And the tempest-tossed Church—all her eyes are on thee.
They look to thy shining, sweet Star of the Sea.</p>

<p>3 He gazed on thy soul, it was spotless and fair;
For the empire of sin, it had never been there;
None ever had owned thee, dear Mother, but He,
And He blessed thy clear shining, sweet Star of the Sea.</p>

<p>4 Earth gave Him one lodging; ’twas deep in thy breast,
And God found a home where the sinner finds rest;
His home and His hiding-place, both were in thee;
He was won by thy shining, sweet Star of the Sea.</p>

<p>5 Oh, blissful and calm was the wonderful rest
That thou gavest thy God in thy virginal breast;
For the heaven He left He found heaven in thee,
And He shone in thy shining, sweet Star of the Sea.
Frederick William Faber, 1814–63</p>

<p>Here are my files &ndash; I&rsquo;ve only typed up the soprano and bass lines for playing on the organ because I don&rsquo;t do my regular practice.<br/>
Lilypond source: <a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/OPurest.ly">OPurest.ly</a>
Midi: <a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/OPurest.midi">OPurest.midi</a>
And the printable pdf: <a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/OPurest.pdf">OPurest.pdf</a></p>

<p>And here is a karaoke version with full organ and congregation joining in.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Te lucis ante terminum]]></title>
    <link href="http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/07/05/te-lucis-ante-terminum/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-05T09:59:57+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/07/05/te-lucis-ante-terminum</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.redbubble.com/people/swissbrandt/works/4662340-flying-south-for-breakfast?c=179607-landscapes"><img src="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/flyingsouth-300x207.jpg" alt="flyingsouth" /></a>Each night our family sings Compline, the night time prayers of the Church.  We learnt the way from the <a href="http://maternalheart.org">Maternal Heart Church</a>.  Since then they have shifted to singing the Divine Office from the Benedictine books, so they have slightly different words and tunes.  Here is the Roman one that most 1962 books use.  In 1974 there was yet another change.</p>

<p>The hymn for Compline is very beautiful. The prayers to ward off bad dreams are helpful when getting children off to bed.  Each new season brings a new tune, the words staying the same.  They&rsquo;re all pretty simple, as you don&rsquo;t need complicated stuff to learn just before bed!</p>

<p>John Mason Neale&rsquo;s translation runs thus:</p>

<blockquote><p>To Thee, before the close of day
Creator of the world, we pray
that with Thy wonted favor, Thou
wouldst be our Guard and Keeper now.</p></blockquote>

<p>From all ill dreams defend our eyes,
from nightly fears and fantasies:
tread under foot our ghostly foe,
that no pollution we may know.</p>

<p>O Father, that we ask be done
through Jesus Christ Thine only Son,
who, with the Holy Ghost and Thee,
shall live and reign eternally.
Amen.</p>

<p>For lyrics in Latin and English go to <a href="http://www.preces-latinae.org/thesaurus/Hymni/TeLucis.html">Te lucis at Thesaurus Precum Latinarum</a>.</p>

<p>The tune I&rsquo;ve got here today is the regular Sunday and other minor feasts tune you can use most of the time.  <a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/gregorio51d606b280f881.81872940.pdf">Here&rsquo;s a pdf</a>, mostly taken from <a href="http://gregobase.selapa.net/chant.php?id=1843">GregoBase</a>.</p>

<p>Here is how we sing it: <a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/telucis.mp3">telucis.mp3</a> [audio: <a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/telucis.mp3">http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/telucis.mp3</a>]</p>

<p>And here is the serious rendition with the music scrolling past.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[7th Sunday post pentecost]]></title>
    <link href="http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/07/03/7th-sunday-post-pentecost/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-03T11:51:25+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/07/03/7th-sunday-post-pentecost</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/sermononmount-211x300.jpg" alt="sermononmount" />Another Gospel from the Sermon on the Mount.</p>

<blockquote><p>A frúctibus eórum cognoscétis eos.</p></blockquote>

<p>By their fruits you shall know them.</p>

<p>At that time, Jesus said to His disciples: Beware of false prophets, who come to you in the clothing of sheep, but inwardly they are ravening wolves. By their fruits you shall know them. Do men gather grapes of thorns, or figs of thistles? Even so every good tree bringeth forth good fruit, and the evil tree bringeth forth evil fruit. A good tree cannot bring forth evil fruit, neither can an evil tree bring forth good fruit. Every tree that bringeth not forth good fruit shall be cut down, and shall be cast into the fire. Wherefore by their fruits you shall know them. Not every one that saith to Me: Lord, Lord, shall enter into the kingdom of heaven; but he that doeth the will of My Father who is in heaven, he shall enter into the kingdom of heaven.</p>

<p>And here is the Kids Mass Sheet: <a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/Pentecost07.pdf">Pentecost07</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Who are these like stars appearing?]]></title>
    <link href="http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/06/28/who-are-these-like-stars-appearing/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-28T16:58:47+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/06/28/who-are-these-like-stars-appearing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/cartoo10215.jpg" alt="cartoo10215" />This Saturday is the feast of St Peter and St Paul.  So I started hunting for a hymn for them.  If you would like to pursue that, <a href="http://aclerkofoxford.blogspot.com.au/2012/06/hymns-for-st-peter-and-st-paul.html">This Post</a> looks great.</p>

<p>Instead I got sidetracked with a hymn for priest saints, which should be alright for the feast too.</p>

<blockquote><p>Who are these like stars appearing,
These before God’s throne who stand?
Each a golden crown is wearing;
Who are all this glorious band?
Alleluia! Hark, they sing,
Praising loud their heav’nly King.</p></blockquote>

<p>These are they who have contended
For their Saviour’s honour long,
Wrestling on till life was ended,
Following not the sinful throng;
These who well the fight sustained,
Triumph through the Lamb have gained.</p>

<p>These, your priests, have watched and waited,
Offering up to Christ their will;
Soul and body consecrated,
Day and night to serve Him still:
Now in God’s most holy place
Blest they stand before His face.</p>

<p>More verses <a href="http://cyberhymnal.org/htm/w/h/o/whoaretl.htm">here</a> but check the slight change in the last verse.  I&rsquo;m going with &ldquo;your priests&rdquo; from <a href="http://frpaulnewton.com">Fr Paul Newton&rsquo;s</a>  hymn book Pange Lingua.  I think it might be a case of Catholics adapting a Protestant hymn!  Good to see it works both ways.</p>

<p>The tune is called All Saints.  Get your sheet music and karaoke backing tracks from <a href="http://www.smallchurchmusic.com/index.php?RSongID=1369">smallchurchmusic.com</a>.</p>

<p>As for recordings, the tune is so cool, the organist tends to put the pedal to the metal and drown out the congregation.  Which is fabulous when you&rsquo;re singing along, but for learning the tune, you might like this one &ndash; different words.</p>

<p>Excerpts from When the Patriarch was returning:</p>

<blockquote><p>Wondrous gift! The Word who fashioned
All things by His might divine,
Bread into His Body changes,
Into His own Blood the wine;
What though sense no change perceives,
Faith admires, adores, believes.</p></blockquote>

<p>He who once to die a Victim
On the Cross did not refuse,
Day by day upon our altars,
That same Sacrifice renews;
Through His holy Priesthood&rsquo;s hands,
Faithful to His last commands.</p>

<p>I have that down as an offertory, but might make a fine recessional for this Sunday.</p>

<p>And, of course, now, at the end, I stumble across the perfect article <a href="http://www.newliturgicalmovement.org/2008/05/not-your-grandmothers-or-your-mothers.html#.Uc0xh1Tkuyo">Not Your Grandmother&rsquo;s&mdash;or Your Mother&rsquo;s&mdash;Eucharistic Hymn</a>.</p>

<p>I hope this tune adorns your internal soundtrack now for the weekend.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[I will go round...]]></title>
    <link href="http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/06/28/i-will-go-round/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-28T16:02:28+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/06/28/i-will-go-round</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://blogs.telegraph.co.uk/news/damianthompson/100021782/pope-wants-crucifix-at-the-centre-of-all-westward-facing-altars-during-mass-says-papal-mc-so-why-do-our-bishops-ignore-him/"><img src="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/TB2-300x199.jpeg" alt="Pope Benedict XVI Celebrates Mass At Yankee Stadium" /></a>This week I&rsquo;ve been drilling the propers for this Sunday.  We&rsquo;re hoping to have a sung Mass at Mulgoa to see off our priest.  This is the priest who sings the Passion on Palm Sunday and Good Friday, solo.</p>

<p>Now, the propers, &ldquo;What are they?&rdquo;, you ask.  I&rsquo;m glad you asked that, because they are one of the hidden treasures of the Catholic Church which should be known more widely.  You might have seen them in your Sunday or Weekday Missal.  They&rsquo;re the little snippets labelled &ldquo;Entrance Antiphon&rdquo; or &ldquo;Communion Antiphon&rdquo; that sometimes someone at a weekday Mass will read out from in the pews, finishing just as you go to pick up your book to join in.</p>

<p>They are centuries old, mostly derived from the Psalms, and they all have music.  There are four for each Mass: Introit (or Entrance), Gradual/Tract/Alleluia (sorry, I&rsquo;ll lump them all together for now, but I know they are separate), Offertory and Communion.  The Communion is often the shortest and simplest.  The Introit is usually pretty straightforward to learn too.  The Gradual is the amazing soaring high point.  The Alleluia is very cool too.  The Offertory is a little less ornate.</p>

<p>So, here is the communion antiphon for this Sunday:</p>

<blockquote><p>Circuibo et immolábo in tabernáculo ejus hóstiam jubilatiónis: cantábo et psalmum dicam Dómino.</p></blockquote>

<p>I will go round, and offer up in His tabernacle a sacrifice of jubilation; I will sing, and recite a psalm to the Lord.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s the sheet music: <a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/circuibo.pdf">circuibo.pdf</a>
(which is mostly from <a href="http://gregobase.selapa.net/chant.php?id=1079">Gregobase</a>, with added translation from <a href="http://maternalheart.org">Maternal Heart</a>)</p>

<p>And here&rsquo;s my rendition: <a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/circuibo.mp3">circuibo.mp3</a>
[audio: <a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/circuibo.mp3">http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/circuibo.mp3</a>]</p>

<p>And here&rsquo;s the way the professionals do it: <a href="http://www.ccwatershed.org/video/10412006/">at CC Watershed</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
