<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Music | My Octopress Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://veromary.github.io/blog/categories/music/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://veromary.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-09-23T11:17:07+10:00</updated>
  <id>http://veromary.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Veronica Brandt]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[veronica@brandt.id.au]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Angelus]]></title>
    <link href="http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/07/26/angelus/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-26T13:36:55+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/07/26/angelus</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/martini-annunciazione.jpg"><img src="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/martini-annunciazione-300x189.jpg" alt="martini-annunciazione" /></a>Traditionally said every day at 6am, 12noon and 6pm, commemorating the Annunciation of Our Lord by the Angel Gabriel to Mary.  We had this in my primary school &ndash; a year six student would read it out over the public address system everyday at noon.  In the Philippines it would be said over the radio.  In medieval times the church bell would remind people for miles around to take a moment to pray.</p>

<p>In Easter time it is replaced by Regina Caeli (O Queen of Heaven rejoice!) which has music, but the rest of the year we usually just say it.</p>

<p>℣ Angelus Domini nuntiavit Mariae;
℟ Et concepit de Spiritu Sancto.
Ave Maria, gratia plena, Dominus tecum. Benedicta tu in mulieribus, et benedictus fructus ventris tui, Iesus. Sancta Maria, Mater Dei, ora pro nobis peccatoribus, nunc, et in hora mortis nostrae. Amen.
℣ Ecce ancilla Domini.
℟  Fiat mihi secundum verbum tuum.
Ave Maria, gratia plena,&hellip;
℣ Et Verbum caro factum est.
℟  Et habitavit in nobis.
Ave Maria, gratia plena,&hellip;
℣ Ora pro nobis, sancta Dei Genetrix.
℟  Ut digni efficiamur promissionibus Christi.
Oremus:
Gratiam tuam, quaesumus, Domine, mentibus nostris infunde; ut qui, Angelo nuntiante, Christi Filii tui incarnationem cognovimus, per passionem eius et crucem, ad resurrectionis gloriam perducamur. Per eundem Christum Dominum nostrum.
℟  Amen.</p>

<p>℣ The angel of the Lord declared unto Mary;
℟ And she conceived of the Holy Spirit.Hail Mary, full of grace, the Lord is with thee. Blessed art thou amongst women and blessed is the fruit of thy womb, Jesus. Holy Mary, Mother of God, pray for us sinners, now, and in the hour of our death. Amen.
℣ Behold the handmaid of the Lord:
℟  Be it done unto me according to Thy word.
Hail Mary, full of grace, &hellip;
℣ And the Word was made flesh:
℟  And dwelt among us.
Hail Mary, full of grace, &hellip;
℣ Pray for us, O Holy Mother of God.
℟  That we may be made worthy of the promises of Christ.
Let us pray:
Pour forth, we beseech Thee, O Lord, Thy grace into our hearts, that we, to whom the incarnation of Christ, Thy Son, was made known by the message of an angel, may by His passion and cross be brought to the glory of His resurrection, through the same Christ our Lord.
℟  Amen.</p>

<p>There are settings to sing the Angelus.  Here is one by Dom Charpentier OSB.  He uses a common antiphon tune in mode 4.  Sheet music <a href="http://lalemantpolyphonic.org/05_temp_Psalm_tone_samples/angelus_sung_PDF.pdf">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Soul of my Saviour]]></title>
    <link href="http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/07/25/soul-of-my-saviour/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-25T21:51:10+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/07/25/soul-of-my-saviour</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/St-Peter-Julian-Eymard.jpg"><img src="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/St-Peter-Julian-Eymard-208x300.jpg" alt="St Peter Julian Eymard" /></a>This is my favourite hymn for a thanksgiving after communion.</p>

<blockquote><p>Soul of my Savior sanctify my breast,
Body of Christ, be thou my saving guest,
Blood of my Savior, bathe me in thy tide,
wash me with waters gushing from thy side.</p></blockquote>

<p>Strength and protection may thy passion be,
O blessèd Jesus, hear and answer me;
deep in thy wounds, Lord, hide and shelter me,
so shall I never, never part from thee.</p>

<p>Guard and defend me from the foe malign,
in death&rsquo;s dread moments make me only thine;
call me and bid me come to thee on high
where I may praise thee with thy saints for ay.</p>

<p>Sheet music available at <a href="http://musicasacra.com/music/english-hymns-in-the-commons/">English hymns in the commons</a> thanks to the Church Music Association of America</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Holy God, we praise Thy Name!]]></title>
    <link href="http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/07/19/holy-god-we-praise-thy-name/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-19T19:54:22+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/07/19/holy-god-we-praise-thy-name</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/communion-of-saints.jpg" alt="communion-of-saints" />This is a well known hymn.  It is based on the Ambrosian hymn <em>Te Deum</em>, a hymn of thanksgiving &ndash; <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MhUUvCxxsuY">here is a recording of Giovani Vianini jamming on the organ</a>.  But I&rsquo;m wandering &ndash; this is the vernacular hymn of the week post.</p>

<p>The <em>Te Deum</em> was anonymously paraphrased into German but later attributed to Ignaz Franz, then translated into English by Clarence Walworth from New York.  I&rsquo;ve heard that it is the standard post-benediction hymn in the United States.</p>

<p>Liturgically, there are times when the Te Deum is not sung, in times with a more penitential flavour like Lent, so Holy God is not quite a &ldquo;hymn for all seasons&rdquo;.  But pretty close.</p>

<blockquote><p>Holy God, we praise Thy Name;
Lord of all, we bow before Thee!
All on earth Thy scepter claim,
All in Heaven above adore Thee;
Infinite Thy vast domain,
Everlasting is Thy reign.</p></blockquote>

<p>Hark! the loud celestial hymn
Angel choirs above are raising,
Cherubim and seraphim,
In unceasing chorus praising;
Fill the heavens with sweet accord:
Holy, holy, holy, Lord.</p>

<p>Lo! the apostolic train
Join the sacred Name to hallow;
Prophets swell the loud refrain,
And the white robed martyrs follow;
And from morn to set of sun,
Through the Church the song goes on.</p>

<p>Holy Father, Holy Son,
Holy Spirit, Three we name Thee;
While in essence only One,
Undivided God we claim Thee;
And adoring bend the knee,
While we own the mystery.</p>

<p>Thou art King of glory, Christ:
Son of God, yet born of Mary;
For us sinners sacrificed,
And to death a tributary:
First to break the bars of death,
Thou has opened Heaven to faith.</p>

<p>From Thy high celestial home,
Judge of all, again returning,
We believe that Thou shalt come
In the dreaded doomsday morning;
When Thy voice shall shake the earth,
And the startled dead come forth.</p>

<p><em>Therefore do we pray Thee, Lord:
Help Thy servants whom, redeeming
By Thy precious blood out-poured,
Thou hast saved from Satan’s scheming.
Give to them eternal rest
In the glory of the blest.</em></p>

<p>Spare Thy people, Lord, we pray,
By a thousand snares surrounded:
Keep us without sin today,
Never let us be confounded.
Lo, I put my trust in Thee;
Never, Lord, abandon me.</p>

<p>*This verse a later addition by Hugh T. Henry.</p>

<p>Here is the sheet music from the Vatican II hymnbook by Corpus Christi Watershed <a href="http://www.ccwatershed.org/pdfs/217-holy-god-we-praise-thy-name-grosser-gott-hh3/download/">Holy God/Grosser Gott</a>.</p>

<p>Here is my easy play version <a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/holyGod.pdf">holyGod</a> (with lilypond source: <a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/holyGod.ly">holyGod</a>)</p>

<p>And the obligatory recording, in case you haven&rsquo;t heard it already:</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Little hymn for the little hours of the little office]]></title>
    <link href="http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/07/19/little-hymn-for-the-little-hours-of-the-little-office/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-19T15:37:23+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/07/19/little-hymn-for-the-little-hours-of-the-little-office</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/immaculate-heart-of-mary.jpg"><img src="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/immaculate-heart-of-mary-242x300.jpg" alt="immaculate-heart-of-mary" /></a>Right now our family just does two hours, Prime and Compline.  I&rsquo;ve mentioned the <a href="http://brandt.id.au/music/te-lucis-ante-terminum/">hymn for Compline earlier</a>.  We did try singing Prime from the regular Divine Office, but found it a bit difficult.  Instead we settled on the Little Office version.  It&rsquo;s the same each day, with minor seasonal variations for Advent and Christmas.</p>

<p>The Divine Office has different hymns for each hour: Jam Lucis for Prime, Nunc Sancte Nobis for Terce, Rector Potens for Sext, Rerum Deus for None and Te Lucis for Compline.  Matins, Lauds and Vespers have different hymns for each day of the week and different feast days and seasons.  The Little Office of the Blessed Virgin Mary has much fewer hymns and most of them to the one tune.</p>

<p>This is the hymn for Prime, Terce, Sext, None and Compline:</p>

<p>Memento, rerum Conditor,
Nostri quod olim corporis,
Sacrata ab alvo Virginis
Nascendo formam sumpseris.</p>

<p>Maria, Mater gratiæ,
Dulcis parens clementiæ,
Tu nos ab hoste protege
Et mortis hora suscipe.</p>

<p>Jesu, tibi sit gloria,
Qui natus es de Virgine,
Cum Patre, et almo Spiritu,
In sempiterna sæcula. Amen.</p>

<p>Remember, O Creator Lord,
that in the Virgin&rsquo;s sacred womb
Thou wast conceived, and of her flesh
didst our mortality assume.</p>

<p>Mother of grace, O Mary blest,
to thee, sweet fount of love, we fly;
shield us through life, and take us hence
to thy dear bosom when we die.</p>

<p>O Jesu! born of Mary bright!
Immortal glory be to Thee;
praise to the Father infinite,
and Holy Ghost eternally. Amen.</p>

<p>Matins and Lauds have slightly longer hymns, but same tune.</p>

<p>Some collections of chant have a shorter version, just taking the last two verses of Memento, as sung in this clip from youtube:</p>

<p>So, for singing along, here is the sheet music: <a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/MementoRerum.pdf">MementoRerum</a>
You might remember last weeks diversion into the differences in chant hymns introduced by Pope Urban VIII.  Here is the earlier, medieval wording: <a href="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/MementoSalutis.pdf">MementoSalutis</a>.  Which is also the same wording that William Byrd used in <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=722E-rjD5Nw">a beautiful polyphonic arrangement</a>.</p>

<p>Those pages are from a book I was working on which is up at <a href="http://github.com/veromary/littleOffice">github/veromary/littleOffice</a>.  A booklet with Prime and Compline from the little office, plus the text of the Gospel Canticles, Benedictus and Magnificat.  For a recording of our family singing compline from these books see <a href="http://repleatur.net/2012/10/10/compline-from-the-little-office-of-bvm/">Compline from the Little Office</a> over at my choir blog.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Veni Creator]]></title>
    <link href="http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/07/12/veni-creator/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-12T22:27:07+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://veromary.github.io/blog/2013/07/12/veni-creator</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Gian_Lorenzo_Bernini_-_Dove_of_the_Holy_Spirit.JPG"><img src="http://brandt.id.au/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/Gian_Lorenzo_Bernini_-_Dove_of_the_Holy_Spirit.jpg" alt="Gian_Lorenzo_Bernini_-_Dove_of_the_Holy_Spirit" /></a>Good old hymn to the Holy Ghost.  Great for just about every special occasion &ndash; confirmations, ordinations, baptisms, weddings, any time you pray for a blessing!</p>

<p>Here is my one page special sheet music: <a href="http://repleatur.net/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/venicreator.pdf">venicreator.pdf</a>.</p>

<p>And here are the words:</p>

<blockquote><ol>
<li>Veni, creator Spiritus
mentes tuorum visita,
imple superna gratia,
quae tu creasti pectora.</li>
</ol>
</blockquote>

<ol>
<li><p>Qui diceris Paraclitus,
altissimi donum Dei,
fons vivus, ignis, caritas
et spiritalis unctio.</p></li>
<li><p>Tu septiformis munere,
digitus paternae dexterae
tu rite promissum Patris
sermone ditans guttura.</p></li>
<li><p>Accende lumen sensibus,
infunde amorem cordibus,
infirma nostri corporis,
virtute firmans perpeti.</p></li>
<li><p>Hostem repellas longius
pacemque dones protinus;
ductore sic te praevio
vitemus omne noxium.</p></li>
<li><p>Per te sciamus da Patrem
noscamus atque Filium,
te utriusque Spiritum
credamus omni tempore.</p></li>
<li><p>Deo Patri sit gloria,
et Filio qui a mortuis
Surrexit, ac Paraclito,
in saeculorum saecula.
Amen.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>There are two popular translations that I know of.  <a href="http://www.hymntime.com/tch/htm/c/o/m/e/comehogo.htm">Come Holy Ghost, Creator Come</a> &ndash; in a nice steady 86.86 rhythm and <a href="http://www.smallchurchmusic.com/index.php?RSongID=2284">Come Holy Ghost, Creator Blest</a> in 88.88 like the original Latin.  They are both really beautiful.  Both worth planting in your memory.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.cpdl.org/wiki/index.php/Veni_Creator_Spiritus">Choral Public Domain Library</a> has more information, including a link to the <a href="http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/15341a.htm">Catholic Encyclopedia article</a> which gives the first part of <a href="http://www.hymntime.com/tch/htm/c/r/e/creators.htm">John Dryden&rsquo;s translation</a>.</p>

<p>Lastly, there is <a href="http://gregobase.selapa.net/chant.php?id=3241">another version</a> of the Latin <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cDhYGdK0KQg">sung by Giovanni Vianini&rsquo;s choirs</a>.  This is the one found in the Monastic Antiphonale, used by Benedictine monasteries.  The story of why there are two versions of so many hymns can be read: <a href="http://www.ewtn.com/library/liturgy/revishym.txt">URBAN VIII AND THE REVISION OF THE LATIN HYMNAL by Vincent A. Lenti</a>.  Basically, we had all these hymns for a thousand years or so, then in the 1500s, the humanist Pope Urban VIII thought &ldquo;that the old hymns were rather tasteless and inelegant and could be improved with a reworking of the Latin texts&rdquo;.  The Benedictines and other groups (including the Vatican) got permission to stick with the old hymns, so that&rsquo;s why they&rsquo;re in the Monastic books.  The rest of the Roman Rite got the humanist &ldquo;improved&rdquo; versions.  One of the wonderful changes with the whole recent overhaul of the liturgy was undoing Pope Urban VIII&rsquo;s changes and going back to the original hymns.  Unfortunately, the Extraordinary Form uses 1962 books, which still have the &ldquo;improved&rdquo; humanist versions.  So that&rsquo;s what I&rsquo;ve given here.</p>

<blockquote><p>&ldquo;Ambrose and Prudentius took something classical and made it Christian; the revisers and their imitators took something Christian and tried to make it classical. The result may be pedantry, and sometimes perhaps poetry; but it is not piety.&rdquo; &mdash; Rev. Joseph Connelly in <em>Hymns of the Roman Liturgy</em>, The Newmann Press, West minster, Maryland, 1957.</p></blockquote>

<p>God has it all fixed up in heaven.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
